## **CURRICULUM VITAE**

# Professor Ahmed Ali 1910–1994

### **PERSONAL**

Born I July 1910 in Delhi, India; son of Syed Shujauddin (who worked in the civil administration) and Ahmad Kaniz Begam (Asghar) Ali; married Bilqees Jehan Begam, daughter of Barrister Rauf Ali (Syed) on 19 October 1950; children: Eram, Orooj, Deed (sons), Shahana (daughter); died on 14 January 1994 in Karachi.

## **EDUCATION**

1930	B. A. (Honors, English), Muslim University, Aligarh.
1931	M.A. (English), Lucknow University, Lucknow.

# AWARDS, HONORS, ETC.

1930	White Memorial Gold Medal and scholarship for securing a
	first-class and standing first in order of merit in B.A (Honors).
1931	Jhallawar Gold Medal for standing first in M.A.
1933–1936	Co-Founder, Progressive Writers Movement of India.
?	Founding Fellow, Pakistan Academy of Letters.
1979	Honarary Citizen, State of Nebraska, USA.
1979	Member, University of Karachi Senate (appointed by the
	Governor of Sind).
1980	Sitāra-e Imtiyāz (Star of Distinction), awarded by the
	Government of Pakistan.
1993	Doctor of Literature (honarary), the University of Karachi.

# 6 • The Annual of Urdu Studies

## **CAREER**

1931–1932	Lecturer, Lucknow University.	
1933–1934	Lecturer, Agra College.	
1934–1936	Lecturer, Allahabad University.	
1936–1941	Lecturer, Lucknow University.	
1939–1942	Co-Editor, with Iqbal Singh, Indian Writing.	
1942–1944	Representative and Director, BBC New Delhi.	
1942–1944	Co-Editor, with Raja Rao, Tomorrow.	
1944–1947	Professor and Head of the English Department, Presidency	
	College, Calcutta.	
1947–1948	British Council Visiting Professor, National Central	
	University of China, Nanking.	
1948–1949	Director of Foreign Publicity, Government of Pakistan, Karachi.	
1950–1951	Editor, Pakistan P.E.N. Miscellany.	
1950–1960	Pakistan Foreign Service: Counsellor and Chargé d'Affaires in	
	China and Morocco (responsible for establishing diplomatic	
	relations of Pakistan with the Peoples Republic of China and with	
	Morocco).	
1960–1970	Public Relations Adviser to Business and Industry.	
1970-	Chairman and Managing Director, Lomen Fabrics Limited.	
1975 (Summer) Visiting Professor of Humanities, Michigan State University.		
1975 (Fall)	Gave lectures at numerous academic insitutions in the US, among	
them: University of Texas at Austin, University of Arizona, Southern		
Illinois Unive	rsity, University of Wisconsin–Madison, Western Michigan	
University,	University of Chicago, and Columbia University.	
1977–1979	Visiting Professor, University of Karachi.	
1978 (Fall)	Fulbright Visiting Professor of History, Western Kentucky	
	Univerity	
1979 (Spring)	Fulbright Visiting Professor of English, Southern Illinois	
	University; also attended several international seminars and	
	conferences and gave lectures at Oakland University, University of	
	Wisconsin-Madison, Northwestern University, University of	
	Chicago, and Columbia University.	

# **PUBLICATIONS**

# **NOVELS**

Twilight in Delhi. London: Hogarth Press, 1940. Reprints: Bombay, London & New York: Oxford University Press, 1966, 1984; Delhi: Sterling

Paperback, 1973; New York: New Directions, 1994. Trans-lations: (Urdu) Dillī kī Shām (Karachi: Akrash Press, 1963; Delhi: Jamia Millia, 1969); (French) Crépuscule à Delhi (Paris: Éditions Gallimard, 1989); (Spanish) Crepúsculo en Delhi (Barcelona: Ediciones Martínez Roca, 1991).

Ocean of Night. London: Peter Owen, 1964. Reprint: Delhi: Hind Pocker Books, 1972. Serialized, in 1964, in *The Illustrated Weekly of India*.

Rats and Diplomats. Delhi: Orient Longman, 1985; Karachi: Akrash Publishing, 1986.

When Love is Dead (substantially revised version of Ocean of Night; completed in 1988; unpublished).

#### **PLAYS**

The Land of Twilight. Produced in Lucknow, 1931. Break the Chains. Produced in Lucknow, 1932.

#### **SHORT STORIES**

"When the Funeral Was Crossing the Bridge," in *Lucknow University Journal*, 1929.

"Mahāvaṭōṅ kī Ēk Rāt," in *Humāyūṅ* (Lahore), January 1931.

Aṅgārē (with Rashid Jahan, Mahmuduzzafar, and Sajjad Zaheer). Butler Gunj, Lucknow: Syed Sajjad Zaheer Publisher, n.d.

Shoʻlē. Lahore: Maktaba-e Urdū, 1934. 4th edn., Karachi: Akrash Press, 1964.

"Our Lane," in *New Writing* (London), 1936. French tr., "Notre rue," in *Orient* (Paris) 2:7 (1958): 113–28.

Hamārī Galī. Delhi: Inshā Press, 1940.

"Morning in Delhi," in New Writing (London), 1940.

Qaid-khāna. Delhi: Inshā Press, 1942.

Maut sē Pahlē. Delhi: Inshā Press, 1945.

"Before Death," in New Directions 15 (New York), 1956.

Prima della Morte. Milan: Vito Salierno, 1966. (Bilingual Italian-Urdu edition of the story "Maut sē Pahlē.")

The Prison-House. Karachi: Akrash Publishing, 1985.

#### **POETRY**

Purple Gold Mountain. London: Keepsake Press, 1960.

First Voices, Twelve Poems. Karachi: Oxford University Press, 1965.

Selected Poems. Gulbarga, India: JIWE Publications, 1988.

#### **CRITICISM**

"Poetry: A Problem," in *Allahabad University Studies*, vol. XI, no. 11 (1934). Ārṭ kā Taraqqī-Pasand Naṣariya. Aurangabad, Deccan (India): Anjuman Urdū Press, 1936.

"Maxim Gorky as a Short-Story Writer," in Lucknow Univerity Journal, 1938.

Mr. Eliot's Penny-World of Dreams. Lucknow: Lucknow University, 1941.

"Failure of an Intellect." Karachi: Akrash Press, 1968. Reprinted in *The Illustrated Weekly of India*, October 1974.

"Illusion and Reality, the Art and Philosophy of Raja Rao," in *Journal of Commonwealth Literature*, July 1968.

The Problem of Style and Technique in Ghalib. Karachi: Akrash Press, 1969.

Ghalib: Two Essays (with Alessandro Bausani). Roma: Istituto Italiano per il Medio ed Estremo Oriente, 1969.

The Golden Tradition: An Anthology of Urdu Poetry. New York: Columbia University Press, 1973. Reprint, Delhi: Oxford University Press, 1992.

#### **TRANSLATIONS**

The Flaming Earth. Karachi: Friends of Indonesian Cultural Society, 1949. (An anthology of selected Indonesian poems.)

The Falcon and the Hunted Bird. Karachi: Kitāb Publishers, 1950.

The Bulbul and the Rose. Karachi: Maktab-e Jāmi'a, 1960.

Ghalib: Selected Poems, 1969.

Ghalib: Two Essays (see above).

The Golden Tradition (see above).

al-Qur'ān: A Contemporary Translation. Karachi: Akrash Publishing, 1984.
Reprints: Delhi: Oxford University Press, 1987; Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 1988.

The Call of the Trumpet. (An anthology of modern Chinese poetry; unpublished.)

#### **OTHER**

"Teaching of Poetry," in Proceedings of the First All-India Inter-University English Conference, Lucknow, December 1940 (Lucknow: Maxwell Press,?). *Muslim China*. Karachi: Institute of International Affairs, 1949.

"The Culture of Pakistan," in Richard Symonds, The Making of Pakistan.

London: Faber and Faber, 1950.

Ed., *Selected Short Stories from Pakistan* . Islamabad: Pakistan Academy of Letters, 198?.

NOTE: Professor Ahmed Ali's contributions have also appeared in *Atlantic* 

Monthly; Chelsea (New York); Eastern Horizon (Hongkong); The Illustrated Weekly of India (Bombay); Indian Writing (London); Internationl Poetry Review (Greensboro); Journal of Commonwealth Literature (Leeds); Journal of South Asian Literature (East Lansing); New Directions; The New English Weekly (London); New Quarterly (New York); New Writing; Orient (Paris); Penguin New Writing; and Tomorrow. [Regrettably, a more complete bibliography for these could not be assembled before going to press.]

#### WORKS ON AHMED ALI

- Anderson, David D. "Ahmed Ali and *Twilight in Delhi*," in *Mahfil, Journal of South Asian Literature*, 7:1-2 (Spring–Summer 1971): 81–86; and "Ahmed Ali and the Growth of a Pakistani Literary Tradition in English," in *World Literature Written in English* XIV:2 (1975): 436–49.
- Askari, Muhmmad Hasan. "A Novel of Ahmed Ali," in *Makhzan* (Lahore), May 1949.
- Bander, Laurence. "The Novels of Ahmed Ali," in *Journal of Commonwealth Literature* (July 1967).
- Coppola, Carlo. "The Short Stories of Ahmed Ali," in Muhammad Umar Memon, ed., *Studies in the Urdu Ghazal and Prose Fiction* (Madison: Center for South Asian Studies, University of Wisconsin, 1979), pp. 211–42; and "The Poetry of Ahmed Ali," in *The Journal of Indian Writing in English* VIII:1/2 (January–July 1980): 63–76.
- Hashmi, Alamgir. "Ahmed Ali and the Transition to a Postcolonial Mode in the Pakistani Novel in English," in *Journal of Modern Literature* 17:1 (Summer 1990): 177–82.
- King, Bruce. "From *Twilight* to *Midnight*: Muslim Novels of India and Pakistan," in Alamgir Hashmi, ed., *The Worlds of Muslim Imagination* (Islamabad: Gulmohar Press, 1986), pp. 243–59.
- Kumar, Anita S. "Twilight in Delhi: A Study in Lyricism," in Indian Literature (March–April 1976).
- Niven, Alastair. "Historical Imagination in the Novels of Ahmed Ali," in *The Journal of Indian Writing in English* VIII:1/2 (January–July 1980).
- Zeno (Safdar Mir). "Cultural Notes: A Writer Committed to Progressivism," in *Dawn* (Karachi), 13 June 1986, p. iv.

#### **BIOGRAPHICAL SOURCES**

The Authors and Writers Who's Who (London, 1971); Burkes' Who's Who;

## 10 • The Annual of Urdu Studies

Contemporary Authors (Detroit, Michigan, 1976); Contemporary Novelists (London: St. James Press, 1972); Contemporary Literary Criticism (Chicago, 1992); International Authors and Writers Who's Who; Men of Achievement (Cambridge, 1973); Modern Islamic Literature (New York: Mentor Publications, 1970); The Oxford History of India (London, 1967); and Who's Who in the World (1977).

Professor Ahmed Ali was an avid collector of Chinese porcelain, with emphasis on artifects of the Sung period, and of Gandhara art and other antiques.

—Compiled by Muhammad Umar Memon from information supplied by Orooj Ahmed Ali